Guide to the World Student Christian Federation Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
World Student Christian Federation Records
1859-2007
RG 46
Yale University Divinity School Library
130
(316 boxes)
The Yale Divinity Library holds the official archives of the WSCF through 1925; later official archives are held in Geneva. Many documents in the record group date from after 1925. This finding aid describes the Archives of the WSCF: General Records. Separate finding aids describe the WSCF records relating to North America, South America, Europe, Great Britain and Ireland, Oriental Countries, and Other Countries. The World's Student Christian Federation was created in 1895 to fulfill its founders' vision of an international student Christian movement which could encourage and coordinate the work of existing national student Christian movements, as well as stimulate the formation of unified student movements in countries where they did not exist.
World's Student Christian Federation
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Biographical / Historical
The World's Student Christian Federation was created in 1895 to fulfill its founders' vision of an international student Christian movement which could encourage and coordinate the work of existing national student Christian movements, as well as stimulate the formation of unified student movements in countries where they did not exist. Advances in transportation and communication at the end of the nineteenth century made realization of this vision feasible for the first time. The work of the Federation was carried out through conferences and committee meetings, publications, exchanges of literature, and visits to national movements by its secretaries and agents. The name of the organization was changed from World's Student Christian Federation to World Student Christian Federation in 1960.
The formation of the W.S.C.F. was a radical step toward ecumenical cooperation at a time when no other worldwide, non-Roman Catholic Christian agency based on independent national organizations existed. From its purely Protestant origins, it expanded its membership in 1911 to include Orthodox Christians. The Federation served as a training ground for many individuals who later became prominent in the worldwide life of the Church, including Bishop Azariah of India, Bishop Honda of Japan, T.Z. Koo of China, Nathan SÖderblom of Sweden, J.H. Oldham and William Temple of Great Britain, John R. Mott and W.A. Visser 't Hooft.
For the first twenty of the thirty years most thoroughly documented by Record Group No. 46, the W.S.C.F. focused its energies on the formation and stabilization of national student movements, calling students to the Christian faith and the evangelization of the world. The First World War and its aftermath changed the emphases of the Federation as social problems, international relations, and the issues of pacifism and war came to the foreground. In 1920, the W.S.C.F. founded European Student Relief, a vast program of social service to thousands of students which lasted for five years. The work of European Student Relief later was carried on by an independent body called International Student Service.
At the High Leigh conference of the W.S.C.F. in 1924, men and women from thirty-five different nations were represented. The growing pains of the Federation were evident as tensions surfaced regarding administrative and theological issues. The leadership of the Federation sought to make these tensions a strength of the organization, rather than a liability. As J.H. Oldham expressed it in the WSCF journal Student World (Oct. 1925): "The Federation has realized that fullness of life is found in the tension between opposites, and that when two opposite but complementary principles claim our allegiance, what is needed is not to surrender one of them or to adopt some feeble and half-hearted compromise, but to hold fast to both and follow each as far as it will carry us. If the Federation is able to keep a firm grasp on this great truth, it will be able to render a service of which the world is in urgent need."
The W.S.C.F. has played the role of international interpreter and mediator for national student Christian movements through decades of changing issues and goals. Its structures and activities have provided a unique opportunity for focused study of student religious life throughout the world.
Scope and Contents
These records, collected under the supervision of John R. Mott, represent the official archives of the World's Student Christian Federation from 1895 to 1925. The official W.S.C.F. archives from the period following 1925, which were located at the organization's headquarters in Geneva, Switzerland, were transferred to the Yale Divinity Library in 2018 and constitute Record Group 46F. The W.S.C.F. archives represented by Record Group No. 46 contain materials dating from 1875 to 1945. The materials dating from before 1895 primarily document organizations which later became members of the W.S.C.F. The W.S.C.F. collection at Yale continued to receive important Federation documents and serial publications following the organization's change of headquarters in 1925.
Received with this collection were the books and periodicals that constituted the Library of the W.S.C.F. In 1919, the Library of the W.S.C.F. (also called the John R. Mott Library) included some five thousand volumes, with documents in more than twenty languages. A dictionary card catalog and shelf list in the Day Missions Library provide bibliographic access to these printed materials.
A unique classification system modeled after the Dewey Decimal System was developed specifically for the archives and the library of the W.S.C.F. in the early part of the 20th century by Mrs. Grace J. Livingston. Mrs. Livingston's classification system was updated and expanded by Miss Ruth Rouse in the 1940s. The organization of files resulting from this classification system has been preserved in Record Group No. 46; the compilers of this finding aid take no responsibility for the inconsistencies, ambiguities, and undue complexities of the classification system!
Contained in Box 2, Folder 31 of this collection are documents that describe the arrangement of the archives, including: the "Key to Alphabetical Arrangements" and "Classification System for Federation Archives." These lists define the meaning of each alphabetical and numerical entry in the classification. Another important document in this folder, which researchers are advised to peruse is "Hints to Research Workers in the John R. Mott Library", which was compiled by Ruth Rouse in 1945. Rouse worked extensively in the collection while preparing her history of the W.S.C.F. published in 1948.
The W.S.C.F. was a federation of student movements which existed in more than forty countries. The alphabetical portion of each classification designation refers to the geographical location of a student movement, except in the case of section "A", which refers to the W.S.C.F. as an international organization. The numerical portion of the classification refers to various aspects of the activities and thought of the student movements. The "600" category, for example, documents student Christian organizations in individual educational institutions and work with special classes of students. The "600" category is divided into fourteen subcategories, each referring to a different type of institution (colleges and universities, theological schools, medical schools, etc.) or a different class of student (women students, art students, etc.). Therefore, any documents in Record Group No. 46 related to women students in France would be classified under D(f)622, the "D(f)" indicating the geographical location and the "622" specifying work among women students. Records documenting student Christian activities at Yale would be classified under B (for the United States) 610 through 619. The (often unnecessary) complexity of the classification system is illustrated by the fact that documents related to student Christian activities at Yale are found under twelve numbers within the 610 to 619 range: 611.25, 614.1, 615.004, 615.1, 615.311, 615.32, 615.444, 615.47, 615.49, 615.491, 615.495, and 615.5.
Interesting sections and items are scattered throughout this large collection. The D(c) section, for example, contains much useful material regarding Germany before, during and after World War I. The D(aa)912E and D(aa)990 sections contain reports of hardships amidst famine and revolution in Russia during the 1920s. The Federation News Sheets in section A950 provide international reporting of personal experiences during World War II. The "700" category documents student life in general and student organizations other than those which were members of the W.S.C.F. The blocks and photographs in the collection include John R. Mott and the other founding fathers of the W.S.C.F., Ruth Rouse, and numerous groups of conference attendees. Also of interest are the World War I disarmament posters in Section B750. Letters and writings of notable individuals are also scattered throughout the collection. Section A961.14, for example, includes a letter from Theodore Roosevelt to the W.S.C.F. conference in Tokyo in 1907. Sections D(bc)512, 518 and 544.3 contain works by the Swedish theologian Gustaf AulÉn. Personal notes, writings and correspondence of John R. Mott are present throughout the record group. There are letters and writings by numerous individuals who were prominent in student work and the church overseas, including G. Sherwood Eddy, Karl Fries, Michi Kawai, T.Z. Koo, Baron Paul Nicolay, William Paton, Tissington Tatlow, W.A. Visser 't Hooft, Robert P. Wilder and H.L. Zia.
Letters and writings of notable individuals are also scattered throughout the collection. Section A961.14, for example, includes a letter from Theodore Roosevelt to the W.S.C.F. conference in Tokyo in 1907. Sections D(bc)512, 518 and 544.3 contain works by the Swedish theologian Gustaf AulÉn. Personal notes, writings and correspondence of John R. Mott are present throughout the record group. There are letters and writings by numerous individuals who were prominent in student work and the church overseas, including G. Sherwood Eddy, Karl Fries, Michi Kawai, T.Z. Koo, Baron Paul Nicolay, William Paton, Tissington Tatlow, W.A. Visser 't Hooft, Robert P. Wilder and H.L. Zia.
The constituent members of the W.S.C.F. varied widely in their size and vigor, a fact which is reflected in the volume of material available for each in this record group. The student movements of Sweden, Great Britain, the U.S., France, Germany, and China were most prolific in issuing publications.
Especially well-documented in this record group are W.S.C.F. members in the United States--the Y.M.C.A., Y.W.C.A., Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions, and American Interseminary Alliance. There are sixteen linear feet of correspondence, pamphlets and reports on subjects ranging from the origins of the movements to conferences, foreign students in the U.S., sex education and Bible study. Of particular interest is a group of materials in section B549.01 which documents the Mount Holyoke Missionary Association, an early forerunner of the Student Volunteer Movement. The liabilities of the W.S.C.F. classification system are evident in the "B" (United States) section; records related to four distinct organizations are mingled together under numerous overlapping and confusing subject headings.
Numerous other record groups at the Divinity Library complement the documentation provided by Record Group No. 46. First and foremost, the papers of John R. Mott (RG 45) are integrally related to the archives of the W.S.C.F. Mott was a founder of the organization and its General Secretary and Chairman for many years. The Archives of the World Student Christian Federation North America Regional Office, Record Group No. 46A, provide documentation of the continuing efforts of the W.S.C.F., particularly in the 1970s and 1980s. The collection contains the North American secretaries' files and official records from the United States Committee and the Student Christian Movement of Canada. Operations of the Inter-Regional Office in Geneva and other regional student movements are also documented. Also related are the Archives of the Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions (RG 42), the Archives of the Y.M.C.A.-Student Division (RG 58), and the papers of Robert P. Wilder (RG 38), Clarence P. Shedd (RG 35) and Luther D. Wishard (RG 30).
Arrangement
I. A000: General
II. A100: Objects and Field, Extension and Supervision
III. A300: Organization, Incorporation
IV. A400: Salaried Officers
V. A500: Organized Lines of Work and Study
VI. A600: Associations in Individual Institutions or Among Special Classes of Students
VII. A700: Student Life in General Outside the Federation
VIII. A800: Correspondence
IX. A900: History
X. U: Photographs and Scrapbooks
XI. B: United States
XII. B(a): Canada
XIII. B(c): Mexico
XIV. B(g): Alaska
XV. B(h): Philippines
XVI. B(w): Caribbean and West Indies
XVII. C: South America - General
XVIII. C(a): Argentina
XIX. C(b): Brazil
XX. C(c): Chile
XXI. C(d): Uruguay
XXII. C(e): Peru
XXIII. (D): Europe - Part 1 General
XXIV. D(aa): Russia
XXV. D(ab): Russian SCM Outside of Russia
XXVI. D(b): Scandinavia - General
XXVII. D(ba): Finland
XXVIII. D(bb): Norway
XXIX. D(bc): Sweden
XXX. D(bd): Denmark
XXXI. D(c): Germany
XXXII. D(d): The Netherlands
XXXIII. D(e): Belgium
XXXIV. D(f): France
XXXV. D(h): Portugal
XXXVI. D(i): Spain
XXXVII. D(k): Switzerland
XXXVIII. D(l): Italy
XXXIX. D(m): Austria
XL. D(n): Hungary
XLI. D(o): Czechoslovakia
XLII. D(p): Poland
XLIII. D(r/a): Romania
XLIV. D(r/b): Serbia (Yugoslavia)
XLV. D(r/c): Bulgaria
XLVI. D(r/d): Greece
XLVII. D(s/a): Estonia
XLVIII. Latvia
XLIX. Great Britain and Ireland
L. F(a): China
LI. F(b): Japan
LII. F(c): Korea
LIII. F(d): India, Burma, and Ceylon
LIV. F(e): French Indo-China
LV. F(i): Turkey, Near East, and Egypt
LVI. G: Australasia
LVII. G(a): Australia
LVIII. G(b): New Zealand
LIX. H: South Africa
LX. K: Malaya, Netherlands East Indies
LXI. M: Lands Without National Organization
College students -- Religious life; Ecumenical movement; Universities and colleges -- Religion; Young Men's Christian Associations; Young Women's Christian associations; Youth in the ecumenical movement; Eddy, Sherwood, 1871-1963; Fries, Karl, 1861-1943; Hoffmann, Conrad, 1884-1958; Kawai, Michi, 1877-1953; Koo, Ts Zung, 1887-; Miller, Francis Pickens, 1895-1978; Mott, John R. (John Raleigh), 1865-1955; Nicolay, Paul, friherre, 1860-1919; Paton, William, 1886-1943; Rouse, Ruth, 1872-1956; Visser 't Hooft, Willem Adolph, 1900-1985; Wilder, Robert P., 1863-1938; American Inter-Seminary Missionary Alliance; European Student Relief; International Student Service; Laymen's Missionary Movement of the United States and Canada; Student Volunteer Movement for Foreign Missions; World's Student Christian Federation; World's Young Women's Christian Association; YMCA of the USA; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A
- A000: General, Series I
  - A001: Correspondence re. WSCF archives and J.R. Mott Library
    - B.R. Barber and Mott with R. Rouse, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - With Dean Weigle re. use of Rm. 90, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hugh Martin with R. Rouse, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Re. disposition of WSCF archives in YDS Library: R. Mackie, H. Martin, R. Morris, J. Mott, R. Rouse, 1937-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Re. disposition of WSCF archives (Box 264, Folder 2196)
  - A002: Correspondence re. WSCF History, by R. Rouse
    - Miscellaneous, 1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 2, 4)
    - J. Mott with R. Rouse, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A003: Documents collected for WSCF History
    - Correspondence of James B. Reynolds with Richard C. Morse and Mott re. beginnings of Student Christian work in Europe, 1889-1892 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Memoranda on the WSCF by various people, collected by Rouse, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Various impressions of WSCF by leaders in various countries, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Rouse's enquiries for History, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Notes made by Rouse in preparing WWI section of History, 1914-1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Form letters requesting contributions of material or reminiscences for WSCF History, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sundry comments on the WSCF History of R. Rouse (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Projected history of WSCF: documents on procedure, preparation, resources, collected by Rouse, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "A Brief Statement of the History and Policy of the WSCF"; other historical papers, 1928,1946,n.d. (Box 264, Folder 2197)
    - Correspondence of F.W. Steinthal with J. Mott and R. Rouse re. Vadstena Conference, etc., 1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Pioneering documents re. Japan, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Origins of WSCF in various countries, collected by Rouse, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Interviews with various student leaders on WSCF history (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - A004: Chapters of a WSCF History projected
    - Memo re. Northfield Student Conferences and connections with the development of WSCF (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Memo on early interest in social questions in British Student Movement (BSM) (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Memo on early attitudes of the BSM on philosophy, theology, apologetics (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Memo on number of sailed student volunteers (1886-1945); investigated by Ruth Rouse (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Memo on post-World War I Federation policy (1918-1920) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Two memos on the founding of SCM in North America (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Memo on the founding of SCM in North America and Great Britain (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Memo on the founding of the German and Scandinavian SCM and the SCM in Mission Lands (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Memo on the founding of the WSCF (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Draft- Federation in the World War (1914-1918), 1940 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - WSCF history by J.R. Mott and Ruth Rouse, as projected before World War I; drafts of four chapters by Ruth Rouse (1912-1913) (Box 2, Folder 21,22)
    - Memo on Australasian Student Christian Union; Memo on forerunners of the WSCF in lands other than North America (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Outline of Early Chapters of Miss Rouse's History of the Federation (Box 2, Folder 23A)
  - A005: Analyses and Summaries of Minutes, Annual Reports, Periodicals (in Section 900, History)
    - Analysis and Summaries of Mott's correspondence with men student leaders (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Summaries and Analyses, Notes on the "College Bulletin" (1885-1886), and the early issues of the Intercollegian (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Memo on J.R. Mott's financial methods as illustrated in his correspondence (A800 and the 800 series) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Analysis and summaries of Mott's correspondence with women student leaders (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Ruth Rouse's analysis of correspondence of Mott/various individuals (800 files) (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Analysis of "Student Volunteers" (American), 1893-1897 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Analysis of Young Men's Era, 1891-1898 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Analysis of American Intercollegian, 1888-1895 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Memo on early work of Ruth Rouse in the U.S. and Canada, 1897-1899 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Analyses and Summaries: Sundry notes on books and magazines, SVM and The Watchword (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Analyses and Summaries: Memo drawn from "Evangel" on American YWCA, World's YWCA and women-student work of WSCF, 1888-1900 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Analysis and Summaries: Memo on German SCM conference, 1890-1912 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Lists of folders containing correspondence of Ruth Rouse, as secretary of WSCF, with various individuals (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Notes on Netherlands Conferences of SCM (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Ruth Rouse's notes on "The History of the Church Missionary Society" by Eugene Stock, vols. III and IV re. SCM and SVM (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - A010: Bibliography, general library catalogues
    - The Student World: list of issues on special topics, 1908-1945 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - List of persons whose correspondence with Mott is filed in WSCF archives, J.R. Mott Library, as of 1943 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - List of WSCF publications with call numbers (duplicate of card catalog) (Box 305, Folder 2841)
    - List of periodicals, reports, books, pamphlets, etc. on file in WSCF library at Geneva, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Information re. borrowing/purchasing WSCF publications, 1930-1954, n.d. (Box 305, Folder 2842)
    - Publications of the Federation (explanation), n.d. (Box 305, Folder 2843)
    - Note re. Rouse's documentary material, sent from Wimbledon to Geneva, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - J.R. Mott Library Directory and Exchange list (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Correspondence of Rouse with R. Mackie re. WSCF archives as shown in WSCF list, A911.1, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - World's YWCA documents in WSCF files in Mott Library, YDS; YWCA, Bournemouth, England; WSCF office, Switzerland, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Documents of interest to World's YWCA to be found in WSCF files, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Notes on WSCF historical material stored during WWII in the cellars of the YWCA, Bournemouth, England (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - List of documents consulted by Rouse for WSCF History in Geneva, 1930-1940 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Comparative holdings of WSCF periodicals in Geneva and YDS (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence of Rouse with Dr. Morris and F. Miller re. WSCF General Committee and Executive Committee minutes, 1927, 1928, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Notes on the above minutes, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - List of WSCF and SCM periodicals at YDS, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Publications of different national student movements to 1907 (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
- A100: Objects and Field, Extension and Supervision, Series II
  - A120: Relationships and polity
    - A122: National
      - National Committee of Cooperation, 1936, n.d. (Box 264, Folder 2198)
    - A123: International
      - Pamphlets re. WSCF's nature, purpose, and policies, 1928-1932 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Pamphlets and papers re. WSCF, 1910-1928 (Box 5, Folder 41)
      - Pamphlets re. WSCF produced by or for different movements (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - YWCA study group material (Box 5, Folder 43)
      - YWCA studies re. Christian Basis of a New Society, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 44)
      - YWCA staff concerns; effect of the war on the life of women, 1937-1944 (Box 5, Folder 45)
      - YWCA studies on prayer (Box 5, Folder 46)
      - Sundry prayer and devotional material issued by YWCA (Box 5, Folder 47)
      - YWCA in wartime, 1940-1942 (Box 6, Folder 48)
      - Liaison Committee of Women's International Organizations minutes (Box 6, Folder 48)
      - Fellowship of Reconciliation, 1921-1923 (Box 6, Folder 49)
      - Correspondence of Rouse with H. Paris and O. Dryer (Box 6, Folder 49)
      - International Fellowship of Reconciliation, reports, 1922-1923 (Box 6, Folder 50)
      - Pamphlet: Christ Our Freedom (Box 6, Folder 50)
      - Pamphlet: Reconstruction Plans of the World's YWCA (Box 6, Folder 50)
      - World's YWCA Reports, 1928-1944 (Box 6, Folder 50)
      - Pamphlet: Women Behind Barbed Wire, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 50)
      - Pamphlet: World Support, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 51)
      - Pamphlet: Supply Lines for Morals, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 51)
      - Pamphlet: Association Chronicles, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 51)
      - YWCA Directory, 1915, 1916 (Box 6, Folder 51)
      - Pamphlet: UNRRA: Organization, Aims, Progress, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 52)
      - Miscellaneous pamphlet publications and papers of the YWCA (Box 6, Folder 54)